SUBIR JHANB: Hi, everyone.
I hope you're having
a great first day
at I/O. My name in Subir, and
I work on cloud messaging.
When we launched Google
Cloud Messaging in 2012,
our goal was to make it the
best mobile messaging platform.
And we wanted to give you the
tools to reach your users,
notify them of important
events, and help
keep your data in your
applications fresh.
Today, GCM is used in more
than 1 million applications,
reaching more than
2 billion devices,
and we receive around 2
million queries every second.
That's over 170
billion messages a day.
And this growth has
been just amazing.
We're always improving
our infrastructure
so that we can scale more,
as more developers take
our platform for
their messaging needs.
We believe the two
most important aspects
of any messaging platform are
liability and low latency.
GCM is extremely reliable.
We deliver every
message that you
intend to send to your users
honoring the constraints
that you provide.
And GCM is fast.
For an online device,
our mean latency
is around 60
milliseconds, and our 95%
is around 160 milliseconds.
There is another talk on
GCM performance factors,
and it goes into
insights on how we
measure and improve on our
performance and reliability.
I highly recommend
going to that one
if you're interested
in this area.
GCM is an integral part of
a lot of applications today,
and messaging is a feature
that almost every developer
needs and uses for
engaging with their users.
Studies have shown that users
that have push notifications
enabled have almost three
times higher attention
and 88% more app launches.
And that means more
user engagement
for your applications.
Now earlier, in the
keynote, we announced
our new mobile development
platform, Firebase.
Firebase is a suite
of integrated products
which are designed to help
you develop your application,
grow your user base,
and earn more money.
And GCM shares these same goals.
We believe we can offer
a lot more to developers
when integrated with
other Firebase products.
So I'm happy to announce
that, as we are launching
new features to GCM, this
year we are renaming it
to Firebase Cloud Messaging.
So what this means,
the cloud messaging
is one of the products
in the Firebase family,
having seamless integration
with other Firebase products
like Firebase Analytics,
making it easier
for you to develop, grow, and
earn from your applications.
And this uses the same
underlying messaging
infrastructure like
that we have today,
so you can be assured
you'll receive
the same level of
reliability and performance
that you're used to.
So what's new with Firebase
Cloud Messaging, or FCM?
Well, we've really
simplified our SDKs.
It's really simple APIs
to start using FCM.
You can reach multiple
platforms using FCM,
and, based on your
feedback, we've
added a lot of new features.
So let's get started.
Our new SDKs are designed to
make the integration with FCM
much, much simpler, and take
away a lot of code from you.
Let me explain.
Firebase Messaging SDKs
for Android and iOS
take away a lot of boilerplate
code away from you, code
that you had to deal
with yourself before,
like registration logic,
subscribing to topics,
handling any errors you
get with our servers
while doing these actions.
All that is taken
care of automatically.
Just another example,
this is-- these
are all the permissions
that you had
to worry about before with GCM.
Not anymore.
Our new FCM libraries
use manifest merging,
so you don't have to
worry about permissions.
It automatically adds
any permissions needed.
And just one less step
for you to worry about.
We've also simplified
the registration flow.
As you know, a
registration token
is the address that
FCM uses to deliver
the message to a device.
Now this process
is asynchronous.
Our libraries automatically
get a token on your behalf.
So when you call
IID.getToken, we
give you an already
registered token.
All you have to do, send
this to your servers,
and start sending messages.
And all the improvements that
we are going to announce today
apply to both our
Android and iOS SDKs.
Our goal is to make FCM
really cross-platform.
Now, in addition to having
SDKs for iOS and Android,
we are also launching a
brand-new SDK for our C++
users.
Now you can have
one implementation
to reach your users on
both these platforms,
and I'm sure our game developers
are going to love this.
Now, we will get
into more details
on how to use these
new SDKs in just a bit.
As you saw, FCM
is cross-platform.
Last year at I/O,
we added support
for iOS and Chrome apps
in addition to Android,
and we saw a great adoption
on these platforms.
And it was a very
strong signal to us
that developers can really use
one solution to reach users
on different platforms.
So we are making it even
easier this year by adding
the brand-new C++ SDK and
with Web Push support on FCM.
With FCM, you can now implement
the standard IETF Web Push APIs
and start targeting
your browsers.
For example, on Chrome,
you can send a message
to your Chrome page in
Windows, Mac, or Linux,
and you can also target
your Chrome on Android.
Let's talk about some
features we've added.
Last year, we launched
topic messaging.
And by the way, this is one
of my favorite features.
Topic messaging allows you
to send a single message
to a large number of devices.
It's a great way to
notify your users that
are interested in common topics,
like a musician or an artist
or a game or a sport event.
All you have to do is
publish a message to FCM,
and FCM delivers it to
all the devices subscribed
to this topic.
We also had a limit of
one million subscribers
when we launched
this, and a lot of you
asked for more, because
you have more users.
So we are removing any
limits on topic messaging.
Now you can have
as many subscribers
on a single topic, or
across different topics,
in your application.
Quick reminder.
This is how you send
a message to a topic.
All you have to do
is set the topic name
in the &quot;to&quot; parameter.
But what if you want
to send a message
to a combination of topics?
For example, let's say you
have a weather application,
and you want to send weather
updates to your users.
Now, some of your
users can be subscribed
to topic for San
Francisco weather,
and some can be subscribed
to topic for Oakland.
So when there is a weather
update in this area,
you don't want to publish
the same message on both
these topics, as there
might be an overlap,
and some users will
get duplicate messages.
Now you can use our brand-new
API to specify a condition,
and FCM will make sure we only
deliver this message to users
that qualify this condition.
So in this example, the message
will be published to users
that either have the San
Francisco weather topic
or the Oakland weather topic.
So it's a union of users.
You can also hit an
intersection of users
by using the &quot;and&quot; operator.
Now, we know you have
all these registration
tokens on your servers.
Wouldn't it be great
if you can just
categorize them into topics
based on your users' interests?
I mean, after all, you
know your users' interests.
Yes, you can.
Here is the API with which you
can subscribe a registration
token to a particular topic.
For example, the topic
name here is movies.
All you have to do is give
us the registration token
and the topic name in a URL,
and FCM will subscribe this
to this topic.
You can also send us a bunch
of registration tokens,
and FCM will subscribe
them when you send them
to this batchAdd URL.
You don't even have to update
your application anymore.
You can just start using topic
messaging from server side.
Similar to the batchAdd,
with batchRemove
you can unsubscribe these
tokens from this topic.
Now just a word of
caution before we proceed.
When you send messages
using topic messaging,
we allow you to publish to
a large number of users.
So when you publish
too fast on big topics,
you should make
sure that, if you
see any errors from our
servers, you should retry later.
And if these
devices, in turn, are
going to hit your
servers for more data,
you should make sure your
servers are provisioned
to handle that traffic.
Do we have any iOS
developers in the room?
We have quite a few.
Last year, when we
added support for iOS,
a lot of iOS developers
asked us if they can just
use their existing APNs tokens
and start using our service.
And the answer today is yes.
Now we have an API with which
you can send us your APNs
tokens, and FCM will give
you back registration
tokens for those APNs devices.
Here's how you do it.
You can send us an array
list of your APNs tokens
to the batchImport URL, and
FCM will return you back
a registration token,
along with a status
for each of those APNs tokens.
Now, you can reach
your iOS devices
via FCM using these
registration tokens.
Really simple.
And you don't even have to
change your application.
So we've covered a lot so far--
our brand-new SDKs, platforms
that are reachable by FCM,
improvements like removing
limits from topic
messaging, API to send
to a combination of topics, and
API to subscribe automatically
from your server side, and an
API to import your APNs tokens.
And before I forget, all
this with FCM is still free.
Now as promised earlier,
let's get into details
on how to use our new SDKs.
And I'd like to invite
Liam on stage for that.
[APPLAUSE]
LIAM BYRNE: Hi.
I'm Liam, and I'd
like to talk about how
to use these APIs in your apps.
For each of Android,
iOS, and C++,
I'll cover the basics
of integrating FCM.
First, we'll cover iOS.
And for all you Android
developers out there,
don't go anywhere.
We'll get to you shortly.
The first thing
that you need to do
is add a dependency on Firebase
Messenging to your podfile.
And now, I know that you've
all been waiting for some code,
so let's move on.
As you already know,
a registration token
is used for sending a message
to a single installation
of your app.
And as Subir mentioned
earlier, we now
automatically get a
token for your app
and handle all the errors
and exponential backoff,
so all you need to do is
call this one function.
And we do the same for
subscribing to a topic.
And we hope that these
improvements will
make things easier for you.
And while these examples and
the ones that I'm going to give
are in Objective-C, we're also
fully compatible with Swift.
To handle token
refresh events, you
need to add an observer
to InstanceIDTokenR
efreshNotification.
This is called if your
token ever changes.
So when you're
implementing this,
you should upload the
token to your server.
This is also called
when we first get
a token on your app's behalf.
So by implementing
this, it means
that you'll always have the
correct version of your app's
token on your server.
Now that you have a
token and have subscribed
to topics, let's move on to how
to receive and send messages.
To receive a message,
you need to implement
the didReceiveRemoteNotification
callback.
Here, you'll get a
userInfo dictionary.
And this will contain
your &quot;from&quot; address
and all your message
payload data.
And to send a message, you
need to call sendMessage.
And here, you pass in
all your payload data,
the &quot;to&quot; address that
starts with your sender
ID, the message ID,
and time to live.
And we will try to send
this message immediately,
and will keep retrying
if there are any errors
until your time to live expires.
Now one thing to be
aware of when you're
using our APIs on iOS is
that we use swizzling,
so integrating FCM can be done
using a single line of code,
and it is very easy
to get started.
What this means is
that we add some
hooks into your app
to automatically call
FCM methods at run time.
But if you want to
disable this, you can.
You just need to add a flag
to your info.plist file.
But if you do this,
make sure that you
call these two methods to
ensure FCM works correctly
in your app.
And here we have a
big green Android.
As you've probably
guessed, I'm going
to talk about using
Android in your apps.
I mean, using FCM in
your Android apps.
So first here, you need
to add a dependency
on Firebase Messaging.
And this time, it's your
app level build.gradle file.
Our Android APIs are very
similar to our ones in iOS,
and we do all the
same-- and we also
automatically get a token for
your app and perform retries.
So all you need to
do is call getToken.
We'll handle the rest.
And likewise with
subscribing to a topic.
To handle token
refresh events, you
need to extend the Firebase
instance ID service
and override onTokenRefresh.
And just as with iOS, here you
should upload your apps token
to your server.
Now let's see how we receive
and send messages on Android.
To receive a message, you
need to extend the Firebase
messaging service,
override onMessageReceived.
And here you'll get a remote
message object from which you
can get the &quot;from&quot;
address, as well as
all the message payload data.
One other thing
to be aware of is
that, when you're seeing
the notification message
and your app is already
in the foreground,
instead of posting it to
the notification tray,
instead we'll call
onMessageReceived
so you can handle the
notification intelligently
while the user
has your app open.
And you can get all
the extra notification
payload by a
RemoteMessage.getNotification.
To send a message, you need to
build a remote message object
and pass it to Send.
Just as on iOS, you
set the &quot;to&quot; address,
the message ID, the time to
live, and your payload data.
Now let's look at
the changes that you
need to make to your
Android manifest.
And I know this has been
a pain point in the past,
with lots of copy-pasted
permissions and receivers.
But now, all you need to do is
add one entry for your Firebase
instance ID service, and one
for your Firebase messaging
service, just like any
other Android service.
And that's it.
You're done.
For all you C++ developers,
on both iOS and Android,
as Subir talked about, we
have an API for you, too.
On iOS, this has all the
bridging to Objective-C APIs,
and on Android it does all the
JNI work of talking to our Java
APIs, and also includes proxy
classes that pass the messages
to your C++ code.
And we've made all
these changes to make
your life a little bit easier.
So to link in the
C++ SDK, on iOS,
you need to drag these two
frameworks into your XCode
project.
And on Android, you need to link
to these two static libraries
and add the proxy
classes to your manifest.
When your app starts, you
need to initialize Firebase
messaging by passing
in a Firebase app
object and a listener class.
Know that when you create
the Firebase app on Android,
you also need to pass in the
JNI environment and an activity,
but these are the only
differences between the APIs
on each platform.
The listener class has callbacks
they use for handling a message
and for handling new tokens.
But we'll give you an
example of that in a moment.
Now that you have
the SDK set up,
how about subscribing
to a topic?
And again, this is
a simple one-liner.
And just like in
Objective-C and Java,
we will keep retrying if
there are any failures.
Here is an example of
that listener class
that I talked about earlier.
You need to implement
onMessage, where
you'll get a message struct.
And that will contain the
from address and the message
payload.
And you also need to
implement onTokenReceived,
where you should upload
the token to your server.
To send a message, you create
a message struct and pass it
to Send.
And this takes all
the same parameters
that I talked about earlier.
Now, there are a couple things
to be aware of when you're
implementing FCM in your apps.
First is to make sure that you
handle token refresh events.
This will make your
app more secure,
and ensure that you always have
the right version of the token,
so your users will
never miss messages.
And second is don't try to
use our new FCM APIs as well
as the old GCM ones.
Otherwise, you might get
some unexpected behavior.
But don't just take it from me.
Hear from three of our partners
that have already successfully
integrated FCM into their apps.
First is &quot;Le Figaro,&quot; the
oldest French daily newspaper.
And they talk about how
trustworthy and reliable
a tool FCM is.
Next, we have Kwaver,
an app to help
you create music and collaborate
with other musicians.
And they talk
about how simple it
was to migrate from their
previous messaging platform
to FCM.
And last, we have
Fabulous, an app
to help you create healthy
habits in your life, who
talk about how convenient
it is to have one messaging
platform that talks to
both iOS and Android.
And now I'll pass the
floor back to Subir.
[APPLAUSE]
SUBIR JHANB: Thanks, Liam.
That was fabulous.
So we've covered in detail how
to use our SDKs, platforms,
and improvements in FCM.
Let's talk a little
about our integration
with other Firebase products.
This is a Firebase
console, and it's
designed to make integrating
these products very easy,
and simplify your
app management.
As you can see, you can access
all your project settings
in one place.
And here's a URL to access it.
Specifically for
cloud messaging,
you can see all your
settings in this one page.
You can see your server
key and sender ID.
And these are the
same credentials
you use when you
authenticate on the backends.
iOS developers can upload
their APNs certificates
right here so we can
successfully send messages
to your iOS devices.
And there is this
notifications on the left menu.
Hm.
Now, what is that?
This is Firebase
notifications, and it's
built on top of Firebase
Cloud Messaging.
It's a very easy-to-use tool
to create user engagement
campaigns, target a segment
of your users, et cetera.
Let me show you.
This is what it looks like.
It's a very simple web console.
You can create a campaign
for now or later.
You can send messages to a user
segment that you can create.
It can be all users
with an app version
or with a combination
of application versions,
all users with a
Firebase audience,
all users running a
particular language
on their devices, et cetera.
You can also send
messages to a topic,
and also to a single device.
And that's very useful when
you're debugging or developing
or testing your application.
And not only can you send
messages using this campaign,
you can also see how
effective they are.
You can now see how many
messages were actually
sent using your campaign,
how many users clicked on it,
how many opened it, and how many
users went through a conversion
event.
A conversion event
can be something
you define, like an ad
click or an in-app purchases
or something like that.
And now, you can
calibrate and see
if your notification
strategy has been working
the way you wanted it to.
It's really powerful.
And all this rich data is made
available with our integration
with Firebase Notif-- Analytics.
Firebase Analytics.
There is another talk on
Firebase Notifications
tomorrow, which is
going to go into details
of all the powerful features
available on this console.
So if you're interested,
please go to them.
Everything we talked about
and all the other details
are available at our brand-new
documentation website.
Please check it out
at firebase.google.com
under Cloud Messaging.
And these are the talks that I
mentioned during the session.
If you are interested
in push notifications,
I highly recommend
going to these talks.
I hope you are all excited
about Firebase Cloud Messaging
and enjoyed this talk.
Thank you very much.
And let's open the
floor for questions.
[APPLAUSE]
FEMALE SPEAKER: So if
you have any questions,
you can go to the
center of the room.
There's a mic.
And line up for that.
AUDIENCE: Is it
possible-- hello?
SUBIR JHANB: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Is it possible to
use Firebase Cloud Messaging
to send messages
to our users who
are on a Safari or a
Firefox web browser?
We don't need the desktop
notifications just
to send data to
those [INAUDIBLE]?
SUBIR JHANB: No, not
with FCM, because FCM
implements the Web Push
API, which is already
integrated in Chromium.
So any Chromium-based
browser, it's possible.
AUDIENCE: OK.
Just Chrome.
Got it.
AUDIENCE: For the conditions
on topic messaging,
you said there was &quot;and&quot;
and there was &quot;or&quot;.
SUBIR JHANB: &quot;Or.&quot;
AUDIENCE: Is there any
plans for something
like &quot;and not,&quot; where I
want to send to these two,
but not this third one?
SUBIR JHANB: We haven't--
that's a good idea.
I'm going to take your feedback.
But we don't have it today.
AUDIENCE: OK.
SUBIR JHANB: It's
&quot;and&quot; and &quot;ors.&quot;
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
SUBIR JHANB: And you
can use two operators,
so you can have three
topics in the condition.
AUDIENCE: Hi there.
Short question.
Do you have any recommendations
to migrate from GCM and APN
to FCM now?
Because then if a user doesn't
update his app, you have,
like, three systems to
manage instead of only one.
SUBIR JHANB: Yeah, there are
migration guides available
on our website.
AUDIENCE: OK.
SUBIR JHANB: Yeah, of
both iOS and Android.
LIAM BYRNE: We're
still going to support
GCM for the foreseeable future.
But if I was writing
a new app today,
I would use Firebase
Cloud Messaging.
AUDIENCE: OK.
AUDIENCE: So do you know what
the foreseeable future is?
Like currently, I have Google
Play Services location and GCM
messaging.
Now I'll have Firebase messaging
and Google Play Services
location, which will then both
pull the cores from GCM core--
or from Google Play Services
core and Firebase core,
correct?
SUBIR JHANB: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: So but if I wanted
to stay on GCM, how long ish?
SUBIR JHANB: You can stay there.
There's no reason that it
should stop working or anything.
But again, if you are
writing from scratch
and you have new apps,
you should use FCM.
AUDIENCE: Right on.
LIAM BYRNE: There will
still be a version of GCM
and Google Play Services
in the newer releases
that are coming
out, but it's not
going to get any new features.
AUDIENCE: Thank you.
AUDIENCE: Hi.
In the past, GCM was only
available for devices--
or Android devices
with Play Services.
Does Firebase still
have that limitation?
LIAM BYRNE: Yes.
SUBIR JHANB: Yeah.
We do have that limitation.
AUDIENCE: OK.
Thanks.
SUBIR JHANB: All right.
Thank you very much everyone.
Have a good day.
[APPLAUSE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]