FRANCESCO NERIERI:
Good afternoon.
Welcome to Firebase
Notifications.
[BANG]
[LAUGHTER]
In this session, I'm
Francesco and I'm
going to introduce why we
believe that notifications
are important.
Later on, Ting Mui,
our product manager,
will come onstage
and introduce what
we have built so you can use
Notifications effectively.
And finally, Laurence,
our launch and T-shirt guy
and developer
advocate, will show you
this product with a few demos.
So let's begin.
Why Notifications?
When we embark in the journey
of developing an application,
we all dream about its success.
We think about
how much our users
will love our applications.
We want them to come
to the [INAUDIBLE]
and want more and more.
Because user engagement
plays a really big role
in application development.
And notifications
are those messages
that pop in front of a user
to grab their attention.
And hopefully, they make them
do something that we want to.
A month ago, I bought
a ticket to a festival.
And this application
is reminding me
that, in three days,
the festival begins.
And maybe I should
come back to the app
and check the final lineup,
or buy tickets for a shuttle,
or schedule the concerts and
share them with my friends.
So notifications are really
powerful in getting the users
back into our application.
In fact, there are studies that
show that users that opt-in
to notifications are twice
as likely to come back,
as opposed to those that don't.
But if we send too
many notifications,
we might upset the user.
We overwhelm them, and we
achieve the opposite effect.
Users might silence the
notifications, or even worse,
uninstall our app.
So we need to get
a few things right.
We need to know when
is the right time
to send the notifications.
If I get a notification
now to come back to a game
and play a new level, it's
probably not as effective.
We need to understand
who we should target.
If we have a wetsuit sale,
and we target runners,
maybe we are not as effective
as if we target surfers.
And finally, what
is the message?
What we are trying to
convey to the user?
Because if we get
these things right,
there is when we grab
the user attention,
and we get them to
do what we need.
If we write an application
and we slip in a bug--
I know bugs happen, right?
We definitely have bugs
in our applications.
Not Laurence,
obviously, not Laurence.
Well, we want to target
just the population that
was affected by the bug.
We don't want to send an
apology to the entire population
of our users.
So notifications are
really important.
But to get these things right,
we need some sort of feedback.
And here is when
analytics come to help.
Because with good
analytics data,
now we can improve our
engagement strategies.
And our marketing and
growth [INAUDIBLE]
people, they can spend
time in focusing on how
to increase our user base.
And our content editor
can send content updates
as they write their articles.
And our product
managers, like Ting Mui
here, they're super happy
they can send announcements
about new features that would
make the usage of the app
even more compelling.
So we think that this is very
important to get it right.
And here at Firebase, we
brought a new product that
will let you do exactly this.
Please welcome Ting Mui to show
you Firebase Notifications.
[APPLAUSE]
TING MUI LI: Thank
you, Francesco.
So let's take a look at
Firebase Notifications.
It is part of the
Firebase product.
And Firebase is a suite
of integrated products
that helps you to develop
your apps, grow a user base,
and earn money.
Francesco just mentioned
that a notification
is really important in
helping you to engage users.
With the right contacts
and the right analytics,
it could be even more powerful.
But the process
has to be simple,
so that people can
really focus on getting
the content of the message.
Sending an
interesting message is
going to bring your user
back much more effectively.
So let's see how
Firebase Notification is
going to help you achieve that.
Many of you are familiar with
Firebase Cloud Messaging,
the new version of
Google Cloud Messaging.
It has been reliably
delivering messages
to Android, iOS,
and Chrome users.
Firebase Notifications is
built on top of Firebase Cloud
Messaging.
It is cross-platform.
It's designed so that you
can set the right target
with the right contacts
and be able to evaluate
the effectiveness after.
It is simple, as you can
see from this console.
Anyone should be able to send
a notification or a message
without having to write a
single line of server code,
so that you can really
focus on getting the content
of your message right.
But it is not just
a form so that you
have to fill out all
the mandatory fields
before you can send a message.
It's designed so that you
can set the right target
by using analytic insight, FCM
topics, or even device and ad
info.
Once you have designed
your right target,
it's about engaging your
user with the right contacts.
For example, use
language so that you
can localize your message,
so that your Italian users
will not be getting a
German message, for example.
Or send your message
so that it's delivered
based off the user's time zone.
You don't have to worry
about waking the user at 3:00
AM in the morning, get them
mad, turn off notifications,
and potentially say bye
to your applications.
Every application has
its own customizations.
And you can do that by using
the Custom data fields.
You can pass in a
dynamic link, so
that you can take the
user to the right contacts
and the right flow of your app.
Or provide a discount
code so that you
can apply the discount
when users tap and open
your notifications.
You've just seen how easy
it is to send notifications.
But is it effective?
Is it actually bringing
more of your users
back, not having that much
of a difference, or actually,
turning your user away?
Firebase Notification
is integrated
with Firebase Analytics
and provides you
with a default set
of analytics so
that you can understand
the effectiveness right out
of the box.
When sending a message,
a lot of the time,
there's a goal that
we want to achieve.
And you can set that by
using Conversion events.
We track Sent and Opened
for you by default.
But obviously, you
can provide your own.
So now, let's go take
a look at the console
and see where you can
find the analysis.
LAURENCE MORONEY:
Switch to the laptop.
TING MUI LI: All right.
So what you are seeing here
is the Firebase Console.
And you can find
Notifications under Growth,
because we believe
that it can really
help you to re-engage your users
to improve their experience.
So this is where you
have all the campaigns
that you're managing.
If you click on one of the
campaigns that has already
been completed-- it's loading.
All right.
This is where you're
going to see the analysis,
the notification funnel.
So there's some interesting
data here-- the number of Sent
and how many of your
users actually haven't
opened your notifications.
So apparently, this
particular promotion
is not as effective
in getting the user
to open the notifications.
So we need to do better there.
And if you actually
provide conversion events
when you send
notifications, we will
track the number of
times your user actually
clicked the particular actions
that will lead to that event.
So this gives you
the basic insight
of notification effectiveness.
If you want to do
more analysis, this
is when you go to Analytics.
So there's one trick
that I would like
to share with you here today.
So if you go to Analytics and
look for Notification Opened
under the Events tab, this will
bring you the default Analytic
Event Report View.
So you'll see the total count,
the breakdown by messages
and topics, as well as
a breakdown by location
and demographic, if those
data are available to you.
The trick that I
want to show you
is if you actually click on
one of the messages up here,
it will actually
automatically apply filters
to all the Dashboards and all
the Event Reports in Analytics.
So now you can really
do some serious analysis
of how this particular
notification campaign actually
impacts your underlying
success matrix and factors.
So now let's go back to
the presentation, please.
All right.
So you've just seen the
product walk-through.
So now, Laurence, our
developer advocate,
is going to show us some demos.
LAURENCE MORONEY: I don't
know about you guys,
but I'm a really,
really lazy programmer.
So I really like to write as
few lines of code as possible.
But yeah, thank you.
So actually, before I
demo, I get one of these.
I got my demo wrong earlier.
I was fixing it.
So let me see if I can--
OK, I see people waving.
Oh!
Short.
So I'm a very lazy
programmer, in general.
I like to write as few
lines of code as possible.
I want things to be made as
easy for me as they can be.
And that's one of the things
that really attracts me
to Firebase Notifications,
because it's just
so easy as a developer.
And so, first of all, I want
to talk about two scenarios
for building applications.
And one is when you're
receiving notifications
in the background.
And I want to talk about
just how easy it is for you
to build a code for doing that.
So the first one I'm
going to show is here's
the code that you do if you
want to receive background
notifications in iOS.
Any other lazy developers here?
A single line of
code, and I mean,
technically, it's not
even a line of code.
It's a line of
configuration, right?
You add a single pod to
your iOS application,
and you use the
Firebase Messaging pod.
A lot of people ask,
well, why messaging?
Why not notifications?
And you may be familiar
with Google Cloud Messaging,
and now it's new evolution,
the Firebase Cloud Messaging.
They are so similar, and the
underlying infrastructure
is used in the same
way, that we said,
there's no point in shipping
two sets of libraries,
because they're so similar.
So if you incorporate the
Firebase Messaging pod
into your iOS application,
you can also then
grow into Firebase
Cloud Messaging as well.
But all you've got to do is
put this into your application,
and you're good to go.
And then for Android,
it's almost as easy.
You just build this into
your build.gradle file.
You're going to compile
com.google.firebase:firebase
messaging:3.0.0.
And that's it.
So if you create
an application--
and I'm going to demo
in just a moment, where
I used Android Studio, and
I did File, New Application.
And if you're an Android
Studio developer,
you're probably familiar with
the MT activity template, which
just gives you a &quot;Hello World.
That's all I did.
And then I added this
line to the build.gradle.
And let's demo it now.
Can we switch to the WolfVision?
So I have an app running
in the background now,
and Ting Mui is going to send
a notification to this app.
Yeah.
TING MUI LI: Can we switch
to the laptop, please.
LAURENCE MORONEY: Yeah,
sorry, switch to the laptop.
TING MUI LI: All right.
So let's see.
Let's start sending
a notification.
What shall I send?
LAURENCE MORONEY:
What should we say?
What kind of notification,
just so you know it's real.
Any hockey fans here?
AUDIENCE: Right here.
LAURENCE MORONEY: Who's
going to win the Stanley Cup?
AUDIENCE: The Penguins.
LAURENCE MORONEY: Penguins?
Oh, wow.
OK.
Who said the Seattle
Thunderbirds?
You're my hero.
They're not even in it.
OK, let's send Penguins.
Oops, sorry.
TING MUI LI: Penguins.
All right.
LAURENCE MORONEY:
Easier this way.
All right, so can we
switch back to the phone?
So now earlier, you
saw the phone was just
sitting on the desktop.
And the notification
has just come in.
You can see it up in
my notification tray.
So now if I slide
down from that,
my application was just called
Firebase Notification 1.
And you can see Ting
Mui has actually sent
the notification, Penguins.
And then if I touch on that,
it's going to launch the app.
And this is the familiar &quot;Hello
World&quot; app from Android Studio.
I wrote no code to
be able to get that.
And that's pretty cool, right?
[APPLAUSE]
I've never had so many applause
for doing nothing before.
This is great.
So can we switch back
to the slides, please?
So that was background
notifications.
And then people say,
OK, that's great.
But what about when the
app is in the foreground?
What about if I want to
be able to do things,
and I want to receive
a notification
and have it maybe change
an activity in my app
while the app is
in the foreground?
The classic example
of this is if you're
using some kind of
IP telephony app,
and then you receive
an incoming call.
It's going to
change your activity
to be able to handle
the incoming call.
In most cases, you
want to answer.
In some cases, you
want to ignore.
And you've got all
that kind of UI.
So you're changing
the context of the app
upon receiving a notification
So let's take a look at
how we would actually
do this in this case.
And I'm still a
very lazy developer,
so it's not a whole lot of work,
but it's a little bit of work,
and it's a little bit more.
So in Android, here's
all I have to do.
OK, I'm going to
create a service class.
In this case, I call it my
Firebase Messaging Service.
Because like I said, I'm
a really lazy programmer,
and I have no imagination
about what to call the thing.
And I specify an
intent filter on that
so that it will handle
particular actions,
so that this class is the one
that will handle the action.
And the action that
I want to handle
is com.google.firebase.MESSAGING
EVENT.
So what I'm saying is that
once I compile my application,
and I have that
service class in there,
if this application is
running on the device,
whenever an incoming
message comes,
an incoming
notification comes, then
this class, the Firebase
Messaging Service Class,
is the one that's
going to handle it.
And this class would look
a little bit like this.
So it's just straightforward
Java code here.
This is my lazy
MyFirebaseMessagingService.
And I'm going to extend the
base Firebase Messaging Service
class for that.
And then whenever I receive a
message, once I'm extending,
then I just receive
this onMessageReceived,
and it's going to
contain a remote message.
And then there's a
bunch of attributes
of that remote message that
I can do something with.
I put together a
screencast of this that
went on YouTube last night.
And one question that somebody
asked me was, well, how would
I generate a custom
notification?
So take, for example,
Android M and Android N.
We have the ability to
have a custom notification,
and you can reply, or you
can do something directly
in the notification.
Here's where you would do that.
You're receiving
the remote message
N. You can parse metadata
out of that remote message.
And then you can generate
a new notification
that you would then render
in Android with that custom
stuff on there.
Also, if you have an Android
Wear watch connected to it,
you can send the
notifications there.
So there's lots of really fun
and lots of really great stuff
that you can do.
And this is really all
the code that you have
to do to be able to do that.
It's you create the service.
You create the intent filter.
Your service has to extend
Firebase Messaging Service.
And then you handle your stuff
in the onMessageReceived.
Pretty straightforward,
pretty easy, right?
And then people go,
but what about iOS?
I say, OK, iOS.
Now, forgive me,
my slides, I tend
to use Objective-C. I haven't
become a fan of Taylor Swift
yet.
So--
[LAUGHTER]
--people are
laughing at my jokes.
This is great.
So my last session,
nobody laughed.
So when you're writing
an iOS application,
you just have your
application have
a didReceiveRemoteNotification
handler on that.
That's the second
line of code here.
And that's going to
receive an NSDictionary.
And if you're in Objective-C
or an iOS programmer,
you're familiar with
an NSDictionary.
It's just a set of
name value pairs.
So there's going to be a set
of name value pairs, keys,
and the value for that.
So as you can see here,
the userinfo bracket
key that I'm doing
there, that would be just
where I read out the keys.
Like maybe it's the Message
ID, or the Message Body,
or something like that.
And then I could do something
interesting with that in iOS.
So shall we see this in action?
What do you think?
TING MUI LI: Why not?
LAURENCE MORONEY: OK.
So can we switch to
the laptop, please?
Actually, switch back to
the phone first, please.
And I have my application here
running in the foreground,
and it's the same File,
New, &quot;Hello World&quot;
application from Android
Studio, except I added a service
class to that with all
the code that I just
showed you on the slide,
and I'm running it.
And now, can we switch
to the laptop, please?
And Ting Mui will
send a notification.
What kind of thing
should we send?
What do you think?
Something other than Penguins,
because I don't really
like the Penguins.
TING MUI LI: Oh.
LAURENCE MORONEY: Well, Sidney
Crosby's good, but I don't--
TING MUI LI: Turtles?
LAURENCE MORONEY: Turtles.
There's no hockey team called
the Turtles, but that's OK.
Name a hockey team.
AUDIENCE: Sharks
LAURENCE MORONEY:
Sharks, thank you.
A former Seattle star plays for
the Sharks, Patrick Marleau,
so I'm a big Sharks fan.
TING MUI LI: Sharks?
LAURENCE MORONEY: Sharks.
They're going to
win tonight, right?
TING MUI LI: We'll see.
LAURENCE MORONEY: So
as Ting Mui sends that,
can we now switch to
the phone, please?
And we should see an
incoming notification
is going to change my activity.
Drum roll, everybody.
[DRUM ROLL]
Thank you for the drum roll.
There it is.
And we see this activity
now that comes in.
And this was launched in
response to the notification.
So in that slide,
where I showed you
earlier on that I've
received a notification,
and I received data, I
have another activity
that I just launched, stuck
that data in a bundle,
so it was the From and the text.
And then in this activity,
I ran to the text.
It was really, really
as simple as that.
We're probably talking
15 lines of code, total,
to do the whole thing.
And this is me receiving
custom notifications
from Firebase Notifications
and actually doing
something active with that.
How easy is that?
What are we going
to do next year?
So with that, so
Ting Mui, I would
like to pass it back to you.
And we're going to talk
about some customers, right?
TING MUI LI: Yep.
Can you go back to the
presentation, please?
And thank you, Laurence.
LAURENCE MORONEY: Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
I get applause because
I got the T-shirts.
TING MUI LI:
--shirts to send out.
All right, so I hope you guys
enjoy the T-shirts, as well as
the demos that we've
just shown you.
We definitely like it.
So we have to show
you how easy it
is to be able to send a
notification without using
the console, and also how simple
it is to actually integrate
on the client side.
We don't want to develop
a product in a vacuum.
So we have been gathering a
lot of developers' feedback.
And there are many
developers who
actually integrated with
Firebase Notifications already.
Today I would like to share the
experiences from three of them.
And for the rest, please go
to other Firebase session
and hear about
their experiences.
So first, App in the Air--
someone is taking a picture.
So App in the Air helps the
user to manage their travel
experience after
they have already
booked their flight ticket.
So they would get a flight
status change alert,
for example.
And what they found is
Firebase Notifications
is &quot;reliable and flexible.&quot;
And they were able
also to really allow
them to focus on the important
metrics of their app.
Busbud, an application that
helps you to book a bus ticket.
They will send you new route
information or a discount code.
And they were able to
integrate Firebase Analytics
really quickly, whilst you are
able to customize to their user
experiences.
Malang Studio is able to
use Firebase Notifications
in their latest application,
Chu Day, an application that
helps users to
celebrate anniversaries.
They have users
around the world.
And they are able to use a
time zone feature, so that they
don't have to worry about
sending notifications
after midnight and
disrupt their users.
So these are some really
interesting real-life examples
and testimonies on how flexible,
simple, and reliable Firebase
Notifications is.
So we have covered a lot today.
We talked about why
we think notifications
is important in engaging users,
what we've built to have you
to better engage your users.
And also, we showed
you some demos
and also partner's feedbacks.
In summary, there are
three key takeaways.
We built Firebase
Notifications so that anyone
can send notifications
without having to write
a single line of server code.
And we made the client
integration super simple
as well, so that you can focus
on getting the right user
with the right contacts.
And with a tight
integration with Analytics,
you'll be able to
measure the effectiveness
of your notifications.
We're really excited to announce
our Firebase Notifications is
available to you today.
So for those who are
interested to learn more,
please go to
firebase.google.com.
Check out our Documentation
and Support page.
We really look forward
for your feedback,
because we want to develop a
product that really helps you
to better engage your users.
So thank you so much for
coming to this session.
[MUSIC PLAYING]